{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Thisalchemistandpursuerofthephilosopher'sstonedevelopedatheoryofcolorhe discussed in the book Opticks. This scientist's MathematicalPrinciplesofNaturalPhilosophy explained his law of universal gravitation, developed using a calculus notation he derived independently of Gottfried Leibniz [[LIBE-nitz]]. Fortenpoints,namethisEnglishpolymath who also theorized three eponymous laws of motion.",
      "answer": "Sir IsaacNewton"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1903, President Theodore Roosevelt set aside this island's Crown Lands of El Yunque [[YOON-keh]] to establish aforestreserve,andtoday,thatregionofthisislandisthe only tropical U.S National Forest. The Arecibo [[ah-reh-SEE-boh]] Observatory, a radio telescope on this island, collapsed in late 2020. This island's capital city of San Juan is the oldest European settlement in what is now the United States. For ten points, name this Spanish-speaking island, the largest U.S. commonwealth.",
      "answer": [
        "Commonwealth ofPuerto Ricoor Estado LibreAsociado dePuerto Rico",
        "Boriken"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the LifeofSaintBoniface,thetitlesaintcutsdownatreesacredtothisnon-Roman deity in Hesse [[HEH-suh]].InhistreatiseGermania,Tacitus[[TASS-ih-tuss]]referredtothis god as the \"Hercules\" of the Suebi [[SWAY-bee]]people,while\"Mercury\"wastheequivalent of Odin. In opposition to the Christianization of Scandinavia, many believers wore charms depicting this god's hammer Mjölnir [[MYOHL-neer]]. For ten points, name this widely-worshipped red-headed Norse god of thunder. ANSWER:Thor(acceptThunar; orDonar) (4) The idea for this work's fourth and final movement was likely borrowed from the work of Luigi Cherubini [[keh-roo-BEE-nee]] and consists of a lengthy coda followed by 29 bars of C Major chords. This piece's composer supposedly told his secretary, Anton Schindler, that its opening motif represented \"fate knocking at the door.\" A famous \"short-short-short-long\" motif opens, for ten points, what symphony by Ludwig von Beethoven?",
      "answer": "Beethoven'sFifthor Symphony No.5by Ludwigvan Beethoven in C minor 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "question": "IndependenceHallwasrenovatedtoreceivethisdignitaryduringan1824-25tourof the United States, and he was greeted with crowds ateverystop.Thisperson,whoelevated Louis-Philippe to the French throne after the July Revolution, drafted theDeclarationofthe Rights of Man in coordination with Thomas Jefferson. Continental troops atYorktownwere led in part by, for ten points, which French nobleman who joined the American Revolution?",
      "answer": "Guilbert duMotier, Marquis deLafayetteaccepteither underlined portion"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This case, whose majorityopinioncitedFederalistPapersNo.78,beganasaresultof JamesMarkhamMarshallfailingtodelivercommissionspriortoapresidentialinauguration. This case concerned the appointment of \"midnight judges\" at the tail end of the administration of John Adams. The principle of \"JudicialReview\"wasestablishedby,forten points, what 1803 case, the first major decision by the Marshall court? ANSWER:Marburyv. Madison(orWilliamMarburyv.James Madison, Secretary of State of the United States) BONUS: John Marshall later protected the homeland of whatSoutheasternNativeAmerican tribeinWorcester[[WOO-ster]]v.Georgia.Thisgroupwaslateroneofmanysubjectedtothe \"Trail of Tears.\" ANSWER:Cherokee(orAniyunwiya; acceptTsalagi) (2) During this war, the burning lights of trailing hospital ships triggered the Battle of Tsushima [[soo-SHE-mah]] Strait, a disastrous loss for the 2nd Pacific Squadron. Teddy RooseveltearnedaNobelPeacePrizefornegotiatingtheTreatyofPortsmouth,whichended this conflict. The Battle of Port Arthur began, for ten points, what war in which Emperor Meiji's [[MAY-jees]] government attempted to curb the influence of a tsarist empire? ANSWER:Russo-JapaneseWar (acceptRussko-yaponskayaVoyna; orNichiro senso) BONUS: The Japanese victory in the Russo-Japanese War facilitated its 1910 annexation of what peninsular realm, led for centuries by the Joseon dynasty? ANSWER:Korea(acceptKorean Empire; acceptDaehanJeguk; orGreat HanEmpire; acceptHanguk) (3) While serving under this general, Dubliner Arthur Sandes led a critical charge of riflemen during the Battle of Boyacá [[boh-yah-KAH]]. A series of massacres committed by Royalists led this general to call for the \"Decree of War to the Death\" during the Admirable Campaign. This military commander served as the autocrat of Gran Colombia until his deposition in 1830. For ten points, name this Latin American \"liberator.\"",
        "answer": "SimónBolívar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thislong-timepresidentofVenezuelaestablisheda2008commissiontoinvestigate if Bolívar was assassinated. This socialist president's successor, Nicolás Maduro, faced a disputed election in 2019 with Juan Guaidó [[gwy-DOH]].",
        "answer": "HugoChavezor Hugo RafaelChávezFrías 2021-22 C Set History"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's tweet claiminghecouldtakehiscompany\"privateat$420pershare\"led to him paying 40 million dollars in penalties to the Securities and Exchange Commission. This man's \"Boring Company\" is testing intra-city travel through the experimental \"Hyperloop System,\" and that company broke off from this businessman's otherenterprise, SpaceX. AsofSeptember2021,thewealthiestmanonearthis,fortenpoints,whichCEOand founder of Tesla?",
        "answer": "ElonMuskor Elon ReeveMusk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Musk passed which Amazon founder as the wealthiest person in the world?",
        "answer": [
          "JeffBezosor Jeffrey PrestonBezos",
          "acceptJeffrey PrestonJorgensen"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Texan Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Namesake of Texas's capital who led the settlers there in the 1820s.",
          "answer": "Stephen FullerAustin"
        },
        {
          "question": "First president of the Texan Republic who names the modern state's largest city.",
          "answer": "Samuel \"Sam\"Houston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican victory at a San Antonio fort defended by William Travis and Davy Crockett.",
          "answer": "Battle of theAlamo"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who pushed to have Texas admitted as a slave state and oversaw the Mexican-American war.",
          "answer": "James KnoxPolk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexicancaudillo[[kow-DEE-yoh]] who invaded theRepublic of Texas before losing the Battle of San Jacinto [[jah-SEEN-toh]].",
          "answer": "Antonio López deSanta Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived breakaway Mexican state named for a North American river supported in secret by Texas.",
          "answer": "Republic of theRio Grande"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Reign of Augustus",
      "prompt": "Concerning the reign of the first Roman emperor, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival and loyal general to Julius Caesar whom Augustus defeated at the naval Battle of Actium.",
          "answer": [
            "MarkAntony",
            "MarcusAntonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Losing commander at the Battle of Teutoburg Forest whose ghost was supposedly asked to \"give [him] back [his] legions.\"",
          "answer": "Publius QuinctiliusVarus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Right-hand man who commanded his armies in the Wars of the Second Triumvirate.",
          "answer": "Marcus VipsaniusAgrippa 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexico in the 20th century",
      "prompt": "Concerning Mexico, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary during the Mexican Civil War whose raid on Columbus, New Mexico triggered a failed U.S. manhunt.",
          "answer": "Francisco \"Pancho\"Villaor José DoroteoArangoArámbula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular moderate president who was assassinated during the Ten Tragic Days of the Mexican Revolution.",
          "answer": "FranciscoMaderoor Francisco IgnacioMaderoGonzález 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following the Battle of Niagara Falls, one side in this war ceased attempts to conquer Canada. One side in this war lost the Battle oftheThames[[TEMZ]]after (20 pts)",
        "recruiting Tecumseh's Confederacy. The Treaty of Ghent officially ended this war shortly before Andrew Jackson's forces won the Battle of New Orleans. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this early-nineteenth century conflict that rekindled animosity betweenGreat Britain and the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "War of1812"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the prelude to this battle, one side scored easy victories at Bordeaux [[bor-DOE]] and Narbonne over Duke Odo the Great. During this battle, many Mozarabic soldiers abandoned the general Abd al-Rahman in (20 pts)",
        "an effort to protect their own camp from being plundered. Prior to this battle, PopeGregoryIIIprovided a loan to a \"Mayor of the Palace\" nicknamed \"The Hammer\" to repel an Umayyad (10 pts)",
        "invasion of Gaul. For ten points, name this 732 Frankish victory by Charles Martel."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle ofTours",
        "Battle ofPoitiers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A raid against this man's village of Bedonkohe [[bee-don-KO-heh]] by Jose Maria Carrasco led to his lifelong hatred of the Mexican army. This \"Tiger of the Human Race\" spent the last 23 years of his life incaptivityfollowinghissurrenderto Nelson Miles in Skeleton (20 pts)",
        "Canyon. Paratroopers during the Second World War popularized shouting this chief's name before jumping out of a plane. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this 19th century Apache chief. ANSWER:Geronimo(acceptGoyaalé) (4) Cuban poet José Martí wrote a Centenario of this man in 1889, calling him a \"Hero in Peace and War.\"PhillisWheatley(+)wrote,\"Proceed,greatchief,withvirtue on thy side\" in an 18th-century poem titled for this politician. Parson Weems composed many stories aboutthisman,includingthefableofhischoppingdowna(*) cherry tree. For ten points, name this literature-inspiring first president of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "GeorgeWashington",
        "\"To His Excellency,GeneralWashington\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Due to using this network, John van Zandt was taken to court for punitive damages by plantation owner Wharton Jones. \"Conductors\" who used this network used \"stations\" as (20 pts)",
        "safehouses often run by members of theQuakerdenomination including Levi Coffin. Thenickname\"Moses\"wasgiventothisentity'smostsuccessful guide, Harriet Tubman. (10 pts)",
        "Fortenpoints,namethisso-called\"railroad,\"aseriesofroutes used by the enslaved to escape to the Northern U.S. and Canada. ANSWER:UndergroundRailroad 2021-22 C Set History (6) In this country, illegal miners who carry green bowls on their backs aregiven the nickname \"ninja miners.\" This country's Dukha community, part of the larger Tuvan people, herd (+) reindeer near its Lake Khövsgöl [[HOOVS-gull]]. The Turquoise Hill Mine is a large copper and gold-mining project in this country, where traditional herders liveintentscalledyurts.Theformerheartlandoftherealmsof(*) Genghis Khan is in, for ten points, what landlocked East Asian country? ANSWER:Mongolia(orMongol Ulus) (7) In an attempt to end thiswar,acohortofwivesthreatenstowithholdromance from their men in the play Lysistrata. The Aristophanes [[\"air\"-ih-STAH-feh-nees]] play Peace celebrated the recently-signed Peace of Nicias [[nee-KEE-us]]meant(+)to halt this war for fifty years. During this war, the statesman Pericles [[PEH-rih-klees]] gave a funeral oration at a cemetery near the Acropolis. The contemporary Thucydides [[thoo-SIH-dih-dees]] wrote a History of, (*) for ten points, what Greek conflict between two factions led by Athens and Sparta? ANSWER:PeloponnesianWar (8) This anti-imperialist openly criticized the U.S. for perpetrating the Moro Crater Massacre in his essay Incident in the Philippines. This Southerner served a two-week stint in a Confederate militia known as the (+) Marion Rangers before deserting. This Missouri man described his time as a steamboat pilot in the antebellum period in Life of on the (*) Mississippi. Fortenpoints,namethiswriterwhose Southern upbringing inspiredThe Adventures of HuckleberryFinn."
      ],
      "answer": "MarkTwainor Samuel LanghorneClemens 2021-22 C Set History"
    }
  ]
}